(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-02T23:09:05.402131",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
しくじりかなたそ！僕みたいになるな！！
Shikujiri Kanataso! Don't end up like me!!
イェーイ！
Yeah!
はい、ということで、コんかなた！今回、教師を務める天音かなたです。よろしくお願いします。
Alright! So, Kon-Kanata! I'm Amane Kanata, serving as your teacher today. Nice to meet you!
よろしくお願いします。
Nice to meet you!
それでは生徒の皆さんの自己紹介を。
Now then, let's have the students introduce themselves.
はーい！もぐもぐおかゆ、ホロライブゲーマーズの猫又おかゆです。よろしくお願いします、先生。
Hello! Mogu-mogu Okayu! I'm Nekomata Okayu from Hololive Gamers. Nice to meet you, teacher!
はい！そして、ラミィちゃん！
Alright! Next, Lamy-chan!
はーい！ホロライブ5期生の、顔が肝臓、雪花ラミィです。かなた先生、よろしくお願いします。
Hello! With a face like a liver, I'm Yukihana Lamy from Hololive 5th Generation. Nice to meet you, Kanata-sensei!
そして、莉々華ちゃん！
And next, Ririka-chan!
はーい、先生！カワイイ、ポジティブ、ジーニアス！ホロライブDEV_ISのしくじり担当？一条莉々華です。
Yes, teacher! Cute, Positive, Genius! From Hololive DEV_IS, in charge of blunders? I'm Ichijou Ririka!
そんなことない！大丈夫、大丈夫！そんなことない全然。
That's not true! You're fine, you're fine! Not at all!
本当に皆さんお忙しい中、集まっていただきありがとうございます。
Thank you so much for gathering here today despite your busy schedules.
あの、カニ奢りますから。
I'll treat you all to crab.
やったー！やったー！
Yay! Yay!
カニを以てね、お礼とさせていただきますので。
I'll express my gratitude by treating you to crab.
ありがとうございます！
Thank you very much!
はい、ということでね、今日はですね、本当に、天音かなた、僕が...
Alright. So today, I, Amane Kanata...
僕がやってしまった過去のしくじりをたくさん話して...
...will talk a lot about my past blunders...
みんな同じことを繰り返さぬように...
...so that none of you make the same mistakes...
これからの活動の参考にしてもらえたらというようなものなんですけれど。
...and can use this as a reference for your future activities.
じゃあ早速なんですが、僕のしくじりについて授業を始めていきたいと思います！
Without further ado, let's begin the lesson on my blunders!
それではですね、皆さん。お手元にある教科書の1ページ目を開いてください。
Now then, everyone. Please open the first page of the textbook in front of you.
はーい！
Okay!
「デビュー直後のキャラ迷走！天音かなたのしくじり人生」
"Character Straying Right After Debut! Amane Kanata's Blunder-filled Life!"
えっ、でもそんなことあったっけ？
Wait, did that actually happen?
あったんですね、実は。じゃあまずは、デビュー直後の天音かなたの...
Actually, it did. First, let's look at Amane Kanata's...
ホロライブ人生の上がり下がりをグラフにしてみました。次のページ。
...Hololive career ups and downs in a graph. Next page, please.
下がってるね！下がってる！こんなに！？えーっ！
It's going down! It's plunging! This much?! Oh my!
そうですね、やっぱりデビューが100だとしたら、だんだんだんだん下がっていって、50%。
Right. If we say debut is 100, it gradually plummeted to 50%.
まだ1年も経たないうちに、もう20%とかその辺に。
Within less than a year, it dropped to around 20%.
急降下しましたね。
It plummeted, didn't it?
すご。そんな、何があったんですか？
Wow. What on earth happened?
いや、まぁちょっと何があったのか解説していきたいと思います。
Well, I'd like to explain what happened.
はい。
Okay.
僕は2019年12月27日、
I debuted on December 27, 2019...
約5年前ですね、デビューしたんですけれども、
...which was about five years ago, but...
うん。
Yeah.
デビュー前「これから楽しいホロライブ人生が始まるんだ！」と、
Before my debut, I thought, "A fun Hololive life is about to begin!"
期待に胸を大きく大きく膨らませていました。
...and puffed up my chest with great anticipation!
なんて？なんて？そんな平らなのに？
What did you say? Even though you're that flat?
ちょっと！
Excuse me!
やばいやばいやばい！
Oh no, oh no, oh no!
あれですよね、膨らみすぎて破裂しちゃっただけですもんね。
Right, it just puffed up too much and popped.
破裂しかけて、まだ膨らみ続けているという感じなんですが、
It was about to pop, and is actually still expanding!
そうなんだ。
I see.
まぁデビュー前はね、あの、憧れの先輩たち一人一人に全部違う文章で連絡をしました。
Before my debut, I contacted each of my admired seniors with a different message.
うん。
Yeah.
くれてた、くれてた！
You did! You did!
おかゆちゃんにも送りましたし、
Yes, I sent one to Okayu-chan too,
頑張ってデビュー配信の資料を作ったりもしてて。
and I worked hard making slides for my debut stream.
資料。
Slides?
そうなんです。え、みんなデビュー前ってどんな感じでした？
Yes. How was everyone else before their debut?
え、もう莉々華ほんと、まだ直近じゃないですか？
Well, for me, it was really recent, right?
そうそう。
Right.
偉大なる先輩たちの配信をいっぱい見て研究して、もう3ヶ月とか4ヶ月かけて、
I watched many of our great seniors' streams to research, spending three to four months...
そこ、デビュー配信の準備しました。
...preparing for my debut stream.
すごい！
Amazing!
いや、ラミィもデビューするまでは、何ヶ月もかけてデビュー初配信の準備してた。
Lamy also spent several months preparing for the debut stream.
おかゆは？
How about you, Okayu?
僕の時はそういう準備とかないからさ。
In my time, we didn't have that kind of preparation.
全然もう。まぁ多少ね、
Not at all. Well, to some extent...
1時間もたせるためにちょっとした工夫はありましたけど、
...to fill the one-hour slot, there were some small tricks,
今の子たちの初配信とはもう全然クオリティの差が半端なかったですよ。
but compared to how they do it now, the difference in quality was huge.
へー、そうなんだ。
I see.
確かにどんどん、どんどんね、やっぱり初配信ってクオリティが上がっていって。
Indeed, debut stream quality has risen higher and higher.
いきなりオリ曲があるとか、オープニングにアニメーションがあるとか、
Like having original songs right away, or animated openings.
あったと思うんですけど、
But...
そんな大事な初配信では、こんなしくじりをしました。次のページ。
...in such an important debut stream, I made this blunder! Next page!
天音かなたのデビュー配信。パワーポイントで自分を紹介。
Amane Kanata's debut stream: Introducing herself with PowerPoint.
視聴者の意見「クッソダサい！」
Viewers' reaction: "Super uncool!"
あったあった！
I remember that!
はい。一生懸命本当に1ヶ月以上かけて作ったパワーポイントの資料が酷評されてしまいました。
Yes. The PowerPoint slides I spent over a month making were heavily criticized.
うん。
Yeah.
そんな僕の初配信の映像がございますので見てほしいです。映像はこちら！
I have footage from that first stream, so please take a look! Here it is.
じゃーん。
Tada!
どうなんだ、どうなんだ？
Let's see what it's like.
ようこそ、天音かなたの初配信へ。
Welcome to Amane Kanata's first stream.
ダサ！
So uncool!
大事なんだよ、アニメーション。
Animations are important!
星マークえぐ。
Those star symbols are crazy.
謎の寿司！
Mysterious sushi!
なんだこの寿司？
What is up with this sushi?
解像度高いな、やたら。
It's unusually high-resolution.
自己紹介していきたいと思います。
I'd like to introduce myself.
美味しそう。
Looks delicious.
うわ、下から文字出てきた！
Wow, the text scrolled up from the bottom!
読みにく！
So hard to read!
天音かなたと申します。
My name is Kanata Amane.
夢や目標。
Dreams and goals.
ニコちゃんマークも真似してね。
Copy the smiley face too.
登録者数5万人、これをね、皆さんホロライブ好きな方わかると思うんですけど、まず、
50,000 subscribers. If you like Hololive, you'll know this, but first...
あの、3D化したい！ってことで5万人まず目指そう、てとこですね。
I want to get a 3D model, so that's why I'm aiming for 50,000 first.
ライブに出演してコールアンドレスポンスをやりたい。
I want to perform in concerts and do call and response.
あれね、ちょっとね、夢ですね。
That is indeed my dream.
ま、今のパワーポイントの準備に1ヶ月ガチでかけてます。
Well, I spent a whole month making that PowerPoint.
ヤバすぎる！
That's insane!
すごい言われましたね、同期にも。その1ヶ月、他のことできたらだろう、とか。
My gen-mates even told me, "You could've done other things in that month."
色々言われたんですけど、ちょっと皆さん、どうでしたか？おしゃれでした？
They said a lot, but what did you all think? Was it stylish?
正直に、莉々華、どうだった？
Honestly, Ririka, what did you think?
それ、くっそダサいです！
It was super uncool!
すいません、先輩！
I'm sorry, Senpai!
やっぱダサい？
Is it really that uncool?
うん。
Yeah.
それがかなたんの良さだよね。
But that's what makes Kanatan great.
ちょっとダサい。
It's a little uncool.
個性はあったよね。
But it had personality.
あったね。「PP天使」とか言われてたしね。
Yeah, you were called "PP Angel" and all.
未だに海外ニキは「PPエンジェル」って言ってくれる。
Even now, overseas fans call me "PP Angel".
Tシャツもありますもんね。
There's even a T-shirt, right?
Tシャツもある、最初に出したやつね。
Yes, the first one I released.
水色のね。
The light blue one.
いや、そうなんですよ。しかもデビュー配信では他にも、全部自分の声で演奏から作ったソーラン節を流したりと、
That's right. And on top of that, I played a "Soran Bushi" made entirely with my own voice...
尖ったデビュー配信をね、やっぱりせねば、とやっておりましたが、
Thinking I had to make an edgy debut stream, but...
ソーラン節って何ですか？
What is "Soran Bushi"?
ソーラン節ね。え、見たいですか？
Soran Bushi. Do you want to see it?
見たい！見たい！
We want to see it! We want to see it!
映像があるのでご覧ください。
I have the video, so please take a look.
ソーラン節（全部僕の声）
Soran Bushi (All my own voice)
コールも黄色くなってて。
The text for the calls turns yellow.
ホロライブはアイドル路線...
Hololive is an idol path...
すごい！すごい！
Amazing! Amazing!
低音も高音も聞こえる。
I can hear both low and high pitch tones.
いっぱいいる。
There are so many of me.
始まった、始まった。
Here it goes, here it goes.
エコーかかってる。
There's an echo.
これちょっとね、まだ慣れてない、ぼふぼふのエコーかかってますね。
Yeah, I wasn't used to it, so it's a muffled echo.
一応こう、右側を見ていただくと、みんな「どっこいしょ、どっこいしょ」って一応言ってくれてる。
But if you look at the chat, everyone is actually typing "Dokkoisho".
ほんとだ、ほんとだね。
Oh, you're right.
これ最後のドヤ顔ね。
And this is my smug face at the end.
ぴゅ〜〜〜〜 / やかんやん
Piyu~~~ / You sound like a kettle!
やかん。
A kettle.
こんな配信をしましたがね、実は初めはクールキャラでいこうと考えてて。
I did that kind of stream, but I actually planned on being a cool character at first.
これで？
With that?
そう、やっぱり、参考にしていたのは、おかゆ先輩。
Yes, after all, the one I used as reference was Okayu-senpai.
あははは。これは本当に、
Ahaha, this is truly...
間違い、間違いじゃなくて。いや、ありがたいね。ね？
Not a mistake, not a mistake! Well, I'm grateful. Right?
まあ、クールぶっていたけど、なんかダサいらしいパワーポイントを駆使してね、
Well, I was acting cool, but using a powerpoint that apparently looked lame...
今後の迷走を予感させる配信となってしまいました。
...it ended up being a stream that foreshadowed my future straying.
でも、みんなも初配信はあるということで。皆さんどうですか、
But everyone has their first stream. How about you guys?
自分の初配信、覚えてますか？おかゆ先輩。
Do you remember your first stream, Okayu-senpai?
覚えてますよ。まあ、若かった。
I remember. Well, I was young.
今も若いですよ！今も若い！
You're still young now! You're still young!
もう7年目かな、今。
I think it's my 7th year now.
7年の経過と思うと、まあそれは確かに、時間が経って大人になっているか。
7 years! Thinking about 7 years, time has passed and we've become adults.
うん、それは感じるかな。
Yeah, I guess I feel that.
そう。デビュー配信もね、僕も終わり。ダサいと言われつつも、1週間後に、あの、先ほど夢で、ね、掲げました登録者5万人を達成し、
Right. My debut stream ended, and while being called lame, one week later, I achieved my dream goal of 50,000 subscribers.
出だしは非常に順調だったんですが、僕はこういう気持ちを抱くようになります。次のページ！
The start was very smooth, but I started to have these feelings. Next page!
プレッシャーだな。プレッシャーだ。
It's pressure. It's pressure.
わかる〜。
I understand~
やっぱり、あの、ホロライブというところに所属させていただいたことによる、あの、リスナーさん、数字とかってあったので、
After all, because of belonging to Hololive, there were viewers and numbers, so...
特にその、デビューして何もしてないから、「いいのかな、これで？」っていうのを感じたりしましたね。
...especially since I hadn't done anything after debuting, I felt, "Is this okay?"
皆さんはデビューしたてん時ってどうでしたか？
How were you guys when you just debuted?
ラミィは、もうそれこそ4期生が盛り上がってるところでデビューをしたので、
For Lamy, since I debuted right when the 4th generation was really hyped up...
プレッシャーもすごかったし、結構批判的な意見も多かった。
...the pressure was intense, and there were quite a lot of critical opinions too.
いや、もう、あの、ゴキブリの5期生とか。
Like, "Cockroach 5th generation."
すごいね、結構、才能なしみたいな。
A lot, like "talentless".
すごい言われましたよ。
I was told that a lot.
でもやっぱり、先輩が築き上げてきたものに乗っかってる感じだったので、
But after all, it felt like riding on what our predecessors built up...
なんか気持ちはわかる。プレッシャーがすごかった。
...so, I kind of understand the feeling. The pressure was intense.
おかゆ先輩あった？プレッシャー。
Did Okayu-senpai have pressure?
いや、僕が入った時は、もうそんなね、まだまだ人も少なくて。
No, when I joined, there were still very few people.
もう「大空スバル選手権」の前日に、大空スバルのモノマネの練習をするだけで1時間枠取ったりしてたから。
Just the day before the "Oozora Subaru Championship", I took a 1-hour slot just practicing Subaru's impression.
プレッシャー感じなくていいからマジで！おもしろ！
You really don't need to feel pressure! That's hilarious!
いいな、古き良きホロライブを感じますね。
Nice, it feels like the good old Hololive.
そんなこともありましたよ。
Things like that did happen.
僕もね、やっぱりデビュー直後だったんで、特にね、先輩たちにもなんか恩返ししたいとか、リスナーさんにも何かとか、そういうことをね、凄く考えていました。
Since I was also right after debuting, I was thinking deeply about wanting to give back to the seniors, and do something for the viewers.
そして、この考えが悪い方に働いてしまい、その結果、僕はこうなってしまいます。次のページ！
And this way of thinking backfired, and as a result, I ended up like this. Next page!
デビュー直後のキャラ迷走、気合いが完全に空回りしていた、暗黒の初期かなた時代！
Character straying right after debuting, eagerness completely spinning in place—the dark "early Kanata" era!
暗黒ですか。
Dark?
もう、とんでもない暗黒の時代でした。
It was a truly terrible dark era.
初期かなたがどんな感じだったのか、デビュー当時の状況を説明しますと、
To explain what early Kanata was like back during my debut...
当時はARKというゲームが大流行してましてね。
At that time, a game called ARK was extremely popular.
で、僕はゲームに慣れていなかったんで、ゲームもワタワタしつつ、コラボもしたり、喋りもいっぱい頑張って、でもコメントも拾わなきゃ、と全部やろうとしたら、
And I wasn't used to games, so while flustered by the game, doing collabs, trying hard to talk, and also having to read comments—trying to do everything...
先輩が喋ってるのにコメントを読んだりとか、空気が読めていない初期かなたが誕生してしまったと。本当にね、
...reading comments while seniors were talking—an early Kanata who couldn't read the room was born.
がむしゃらすぎて、焦りから異常に空気が読めてないのに、無駄に積極的に話しかけてくる、だる絡みの初期かなた。
I was too reckless; out of panic, I couldn't read the room at all, yet I kept proactively starting conversations in an annoying way.
これね、結構、見てて、見てたんだけど、ちょっと苦しくなる。胸がキュッてなる。
This, actually, I was watching it, but it makes you feel a bit painful. Your chest tightens.
ちょっとあの、共感性羞恥と、「あ、この子...」っていう、その、悪意がないのは多分伝わるので、キュッとなる系ではありますね。
There's a bit of secondhand embarrassment, and like, "Oh, this girl..." Since the lack of malice gets through, it is the heart-wrenching type.
頑張ろうとしてた感じが...
The feeling of trying hard...
ですね。おかゆ先輩、あの、初期かなた時代の僕って覚えてますか？
Indeed. Okayu-senpai, do you remember me during my early Kanata era?
いや、僕、実は、ARKって1回くらいしか参加してないから、
Actually, I only participated in ARK about once, so...
配信中のかなたんより、配信してないかなたんと関わる方が多かったんですよ。
...I interacted with Kanata-tan off-stream more than when she was streaming.
そう。だから、配信してないかなたんは、今とあんまり変わんないと思う。
So off-stream Kanata-tan wasn't much different from now, I think.
ええ、そうなんですね、実は。配信外では普通だったので、「なんで配信中はこんなおかしくて、裏では普通に話せるのに、あなたなんでなの？」っていうのを、実はホロメンに言われたこともありました。
Actually, yes. I was normal off-stream, so I was actually told by Holomembers, "Why are you so weird on stream but normal behind the scenes? Why are you like this?"
なんでそんなおかしくなっちゃうの？っていう。
Like, "Why do you become so weird?"
まあ、でもその初期かなたを見たリスナーの反応はと言うと、次のページ！
Well, but as for the listeners' reactions to seeing that early Kanata—next page!
「推しに絡まないで欲しい」「早く辞めろ」
"Don't get involved with my oshi." "Quit already."
ね。もちろん応援してくれる人もたくさんいたんですけど、実はこれ、あの配信開始をする前、待機所の状態でコメントが大荒れしたこともあって。
Of course, there were many people supporting me, but actually, even before the stream started, during the waiting room phase, the comments completely blew up sometimes.
500人ぐらいの人がず〜っと言い合いをする
...where about 500 people would constantly argue.
えーっ
Whoa...
こともあるほど やっぱりリスナーさんから ちょっと嫌われてる時期ありましたね
There was actually a period of time when I was somewhat disliked by the viewers.
ああー そうなんだ
Oh, really?
今じゃ考えられないけど
It's hard to imagine that now.
いやいやそんなことないんですけど これ具体的にね どんな感じだったかと言いますと
No, it's true. To give you some specifics of how it was...
コラボの流れをぶった斬ってコメントを読んでしまう
I would completely disrupt the flow of a collab just to read chat comments.
面白いこと言わなきゃ言わなきゃとして 滑りまくる
Obsessing over "I must say something funny!" and repeatedly bombing.
コラボ相手のオウム返しをしてしまう
And simply parroting what my collab partner said.
ってことがね 結構多かった
Things like that happened a lot.
まぁオウム返しもね あの
Even the parroting...
焦りから 何か言わなきゃ 沈黙を作らないように っていうのが
...was because I panicked, thinking, "I have to say something! Don't let there be a silence!"
多分焦りすぎて 悪循環になってしまったと
I got too anxious, and it created a vicious cycle.
いうことがありましたね これはもう初期かなた 本当に大きなしくじりなんですが
This was the early-days Kanata. It was a major blunder of mine.
皆さんは 新人時代の自分を振り返ってみてどうですか ありますか
How do you all feel looking back at your rookie days? Do you have similar experiences?
ううっ…
Ugh...
震えてる なんか震えてる
She's shaking! She's actually shaking!
だ、大丈夫？
Are you okay?
ラミィはね やっぱり初期ラミィをいじられるほど 初期とキャラが変わっているので
Since my current personality is so different from the start, to the point where "early Lamy" is a meme...
ちょっと昔のラミィを思い出すだけで ううっ ってなるんですけど
Just thinking about my past self makes me cringe.
へえー
Really?
やっぱこう求められる像にならなきゃみたいな
I felt like I had to mold myself into what was expected of me.
リスナーさんがこんなラミィを求めてるだろうみたいなのに 応えようとして ああなっていったみたいな
I tried to meet the expectations of "the Lamy that viewers wanted," and that's how I ended up acting that way.
ホロライブは清楚を求めているみたいなね
Thinking, "Hololive demands its members to be pure idols," and all that.
なるほどねー 莉々華はちょっと前のことかもだけど変わったって思うことある
I see. Ririka, although your debut was quite recent, is there anything you feel has changed?
いやもう莉々華いまも現在進行形で いまお話しされてたみたいなことに悩まされてて もう今帰りたいです 帰らせて
No, I'm currently dealing with exactly what you just described, and honestly, I want to go home now. Please let me go home.
ダメだよ ダメ ダメダメダメ
No way! Don't go! No, no, no!
いやでもやっぱ一皮剥きたい
But I really want to break out of my shell!
剥きたい 頑張りたいよね 莉々華めちゃめちゃいいと思いますよ 大丈夫
Out of your shell! You want to do your best, right? Ririka, I think you're doing incredibly well, you'll be fine!
まぁこんな感じでね 良かれと思って まぁ根は陰キャなのに頑張って先輩たちに話しかけまくって
So, like that, thinking it was for the best, even though I'm naturally introverted, I forced myself to talk to seniors constantly...
空回りする僕は 自分の精神 素の性格とキャラのズレが大きくなっていきます保存
...only to spin my wheels. As a result, the gap between my true personality and my persona kept widening.
そして自分が表でやっていく上でのキャラクターに 自分の性格に合ったキャラクターに軌道修正することになります
Eventually, I had to course-correct my public persona to better align with my actual self and vibe.
はっちゃけキャラやめよう
I decided to drop the "wacky, high-energy" act.
結局ね キャラに無理があると精神が削られるんですよね
After all, forcing a fake persona just drains your mental health, doesn't it?
ね？ ね？
Right? Right?
分かります とっても分かります
I completely understand! I understand so well!
ちなみにホロメンとうまく絡めなかったとか 配信後に後悔したようなことを経験がある人いますか
By the way, has anyone here ever struggled to interact with other members or deeply regretted how a stream went?
いや 全然ない 全然ないですけどね
No, not at all, I have absolutely nothing like that...
お酒を飲んでねぇ もうすごい後悔して ラミィ先輩にあのDiscordで
I got drunk, and I regretted it so much that I sent Lamy-senpai a Discord DM...
本当に申し訳ございませんでした よろしければまた一緒に遊んでいただけると嬉しいです
...saying, "I'm truly sorry. If you're willing, I'd be honored if we could hang out again."
つい 今年の話ですね
That literally just happened this year!
一時期気持ちがどん底まで落ち続けてしまいましたが 迷走しながらも配信を頑張って続けることで 僕にプラスの影響が起きていきます
After all those struggles, my mood hit rock bottom, but by pushing through and keeping on streaming...
配信を続ける中でキャラが定着
...it actually started having a positive impact on me! Next page! "My personality became established as I kept streaming!"
ということでね 長い時間をかけつつではありますが 配信の中でできた関係性やホロメンにいじってもらって
So, though it took quite a while, through the relationships built during streams and other members teasing me...
いい感じでキャラが定着したり 自分のことをみんなに知ってもらったりして 配信がだんだんだんだんやりやすくなっていきます
...my persona settled in nicely. People got to know the real me, and streaming gradually became much easier.
配信で定着した天音かなたのキャラがこちら 次のページ
Here are the Amane Kanata traits that got established through streaming! Next page!
センスなしキャラ 握力ゴリラキャラ ツッコミキャラ
"No-sense fashion," "Grip Gorilla," and "Tsukkomi."
これぞかなた 今のかなたんだよね
That is classic Kanata! That's the Kanatan we know today!
ま センスなしキャラについてね 僕はちょっと認めてないんですけど
Well, as for the "no-sense fashion" trait, I don't really agree with that...
周りからダサいと言われた代表的なものがたくさんあるんですよ
...but there are plenty of iconic examples where people have called me uncool.
PP天使 洋服がダサい
Like "PP Tenshi," "simply uncool fashion..."
あとはトレンド入りしたかなたやめろという
...and "Kanata, stop it," which actually trended on X.
はい PP天使は先ほど紹介しましたが 皆さん僕のセンスなしキャラということで思い当たる節あったりしますか
We already covered PP Tenshi, but does anyone here have any thoughts on my lack of fashion sense?
いやー ないよね
No way! Of course not!
いやでも あるっちゃあるというか
Well, actually, there kind of is...
一時期ね かなたんの洋服について話し合うDiscordのグループがあったりとかね
At one point, there was a Discord group specifically to discuss Kanatan's outfits.
あの ラミィとミオ先輩とマリンを集めて突然作って
I suddenly created that group with Lamy, Mio-senpai, and Marine...
洋服がダサいって言われるんで おしゃれな洋服 ネットで買える を教えてください
...and asked, "People say my fashion is terrible, so please recommend some trendy clothes I can buy online."
外に買いに行かないんだ ネットで買えるのが大事なんだ
You refuse to go out shopping! Online is the key!
行きたくなかった
I didn't want to go outside.
ちなみにさっき かなたやめろ がトレンド入りしたっておっしゃってたと思うんですけど あれは一体何なんですか
By the way, you mentioned earlier that "Kanata, stop it" trended. What exactly was that?
これはですね 僕のメンバーシップの名前を付ける時の話なんですけど
Well, that was when I was deciding on a name for my YouTube membership.
元々 名前の候補が3つありまして
I had three candidates to choose from.
かなたーず THEかなた かなたふぁんくらぶ
"Kanata-s," "THE Kanata," and "Kanata Fan Club."
これはどうですか 可愛いよね
What do you think of this? Cute, right?
これは… まぁ、うん…
This is... Well, yeah...
まぁ こんな感じでね まぁ候補がありまして これを見た
Well, there were these candidates, and when people saw this...
リスナーさんの反応がこちら！
Here is the listeners' reaction!
全部ダサいってすごい
"They're all tacky" is amazing.
ここまで悩むアンケートは初めて
This is the first poll where I've struggled this much.
センスが息をしていない
Their sense of style is dead.
ボロクソじゃん！ 厳しいな
That's brutal! / How harsh...
悩んでアンケート入れられないと。 なるほどね。
They're struggling so much they can't even vote. / Ah, I see.
ねー、ネーミングセンスがダサすぎたということで、この時「かなたやめろ」のハッシュタグがつけられ、
Because my naming sense was so tacky, the hashtag "#KanataStopIt" was created,
なんと日本のトレンドに入ります。
and amazingly, it trended in Japan!
恥ずかしいな。 なんでだよ、と。
How embarrassing. / Why though?!
おかしいでしょ。でも、どの名前がいいかなって当時のTwitterで投票してもらったんですけど、
It's crazy, right? But I held a poll on Twitter back then asking which name they preferred,
その結果がこうなります。
and here are the results.
「THEかなた」が選ばれたと。
"THE Kanata" was chosen.
でも、なんか全部ほぼ一緒で、みんな悩んでる。
But they're all almost equal. Everyone was really struggling.
ちょっとね、僅差なの！
It was a really close margin!
大接戦の末、「THEかなた」に決定したんですよね。
After a fierce battle, "THE Kanata" was decided.
悩んだだろうな、これみんな。
Everyone must have really struggled with this.
そう、みんな悩みましたね。
Yes, everyone struggled.
まぁ、結局時を経て、えーっと去年あたりですかね、「THEかなた」が
Well, eventually, over time... I think it was around last year...
ダサいことに私は気づきました。
I realized that "THE Kanata" is actually tacky.
おぉ、気づきを得た！
Oh, she had an epiphany!
なんか、みんなみんながおしゃれな名前だったりとか、
Everyone else has such stylish names,
ストレートにファンネームをつけているみんなのメンバーシップを見て、
or they just use their fan name for their membership.
あ、「THEかなた」ってダサかったんだ、と思いまして、
I looked at theirs and went, "Ah, 'THE Kanata' was tacky!"
現在のメンバーシップの名前は「へい民」になっております。
So, my current membership name is "Heimin" (Commoners).
よかった～！
Thank goodness!
拍手すんな、よかったじゃない！ 拍手すんな。
Why are you clapping? / Good for you! / Don't clap!
残念だろ！ はい。
It's pathetic, okay?! Yes.
え、でも他にもちょっとかなた先輩と言えばで気になってることがあって。
But there's actually something else I'm curious about when it comes to you.
かなた先輩、握力キャラというか、パワーがめっちゃあるみたいな感じで、
You have this "grip strength" persona, like you have insane power.
自己紹介とかでも言ってると思うんですけど、
You mention it in your self-introductions too,
あれは最初からではなかったんですか？
but was that not a thing from the very beginning?
いや、そうだね。自己紹介で言うようになったのは途中からで、
Right. I only started saying it in my self-introduction later on.
でも昔から、本当に中学校の頃からかな、握力が強くて。
But I've always had strong grip strength, since middle school.
雑談の中で、「握力50kgあったんだよね」みたいなことを言ったりとか、
In my streams, I'd mention, "My grip strength was 50kg," or...
もう「力強くて物が壊れちゃう」って話をよくしてたら、
I'd often talk about how objects break because I'm too strong...
なんかだんだんだんだん、わかんないけど「握力ゴリラキャラ」が定着していって。
And gradually, the "grip strength gorilla" character stuck.
そんな僕がね、今までうっかり握りつぶしたものは、こちらです。
And here are the things that I've accidentally crushed so far.
多いなぁ！
That's a lot!
お寿司、マカロン、蒸したジャガイモ、お弁当のスプーン、コーヒーメーカー、キーボード、Switchのコントローラー、などなどですね。
Sushi, macarons, steamed potatoes, lunch spoons, a coffee maker, a keyboard, a Switch controller, and so on.
まぁ、お寿司とかマカロンは、
Well, as for sushi and macarons...
マカロン初めて食べたときに、優しく持とうと思ったんだけど、
When I ate a macaron for the first time, I tried to hold it gently...
優しく持ったのに、ボロッボロになって…
But even though I held it gently, it crumbled completely...
そのエピソード大好き！
I love that story!
可愛いなぁ。
That's so cute.
あの、この中にある「お弁当のスプーン」ってやつなんですけど、
Um, about the "lunch spoon" on this list...
これ、ラミィの企画に前にかなたんが出てくれたときに、
When Kanatan appeared on my stream show before,
あの、楽屋で出るお弁当がカレーだったんだけど、
the lunch box they gave us in the dressing room was curry,
その時のスプーンをバキッて壊しちゃって！
and she snapped the spoon in half!
折れたんだよ、勝手に！
It just broke on its own!
普通に食べてるだけでスプーン壊してて。
She broke the spoon just by eating normally.
そうなんです。
Yes, that's true.
そう、びっくりしましたね。
Yeah, I was really shocked.
家ではあれですか、石のスプーンとか使ってる？
Do you use stone spoons or something at home?
鉄のスプーン！ 石のスプーンじゃないですよ。
A metal spoon! Not a stone spoon.
鉄すら壊す？
Do you even break metal?
ちゃんと割り箸とか使いますけど、たまに割り箸も割れるけど、
I use disposable chopsticks, though sometimes they snap too...
えぇ～！
Wow!
そうですね、スプーン真っ二つ事件は、楽屋でこれやったのは2回ありますね。
Yeah, the "spoon snapped in half" incident... I've done that in dressing rooms twice.
やば～い！
Crazy!
怖い。
Scary.
そして、ちょっと前、配信の流れで握力を計測した結果がこちらでございます。
And here are the results from when I measured my grip strength on a stream a while back.
やばー！
Wow!
55.9kgですね。 ゴリラやん！ やば。
It was 55.9kg. / You're a gorilla! / Crazy.
これは配信でお酒をね、珍しく飲んだ時に、
This was during a stream where I was drinking alcohol, which is rare for me,
「酔ってリミッター外れてんじゃない？」みたいなノリで、
and they joked, "Maybe being drunk turned off your limiters?"
握力計が僕のお家にあるので測ってみたんですけど、
I have a dynamometer at home, so I measured it...
55.9kgの新記録が出まして、
And I got a new record of 55.9kg.
これはレスリングの霊長類最強女子の吉田沙保里さんが、
This is actually... Yoshida Saori, the "strongest primate woman" in wrestling,
あるテレビ番組で計測したのが55kgだったと。
registered 55kg on a TV show.
おいおいおいおい、超えてる！
Hey, hey, hey, you beat her!
それ超えてます。
I beat her.
ちょっと握手してみます？
Want to try shaking hands?
怖い怖い。
Scary, scary!
ラミィ、ラミィとか… いやいや、ラミィは前に握手したことあるんで…
How about Lamy? / No, no, I've shaken hands with you before...
あ、新人ちゃん。
Ah, the newbie.
え、あの、私握力7kgだったんですけど…
Um... my grip strength was only 7kg...
一回僕を壊す気で来てください。
Just try to crush my hand with everything you've got.
8倍？ え、いきますよ。
Eight times? Okay, here I go.
8倍。 おらー！
Eight times. / Oraaa!
もっと本気で来い！ おらー！
Come on, try harder! / Oraaa!
あー！！
Aaaaaah!
う、腕があああ！
M-My arm is...!
力の入れ方ってものを教えてやる。
I'll show you how to apply force.
怖い怖い、やめて！ やめてください！
Scary, scary! Stop! / Please stop!
莉々華、大丈夫？動く？
Ririka, are you okay? Can you move it?
大丈夫です。耐えときました。
I'm okay. I managed to survive.
いや、よかった。もうちょっとで壊すところでしたね。
Good. I almost broke it.
危ない危ない。
Dangerous, dangerous.
本当にホロメンは力の弱い子が多いので、
The members of Hololive are mostly weaklings,
僕がおかしいような雰囲気がよく漂いますが、 おかしいけどな。
so I'm always treated like the weird one. / But you are weird.
ま、そしてそんなキャラと「ツッコミキャラ」、大きなターンニングポイントとなりました。
Anyway, that character and the "tsukkomi" character reached a major turning point.
うんうん。
Uh-huh.
で、このツッコミキャラなんですけど、当時マイクラのホロ鯖内に「かなた城」お城をね、建設していた僕なんですけど、
So, regarding this straight-man character... Back then, I was building "Kanata Castle" on the Hololive Minecraft server.
それを見たフレア先輩が、「かなた学校建設予定地」と看板を書きました。学校に見えたんですよね。
Senpai Flare saw it and wrote "Future Site of Kanata School" on a sign. Apparently it looked like a school.
「学校じゃねーから、これ！」と思わず言ったと。
And I instinctively retorted, "It's not a school!"
そしたら、みこ先輩も来て、「AO入学可能」と。
Then Miko-senpai also came and added, "AO Admission Available."
で、学校イジりのボケが続いたので、「学校じゃねーよ！」とね、ツッコミ続けたと。
Since they kept making "school" jokes, I kept retorting, "It's not a school!"
いいね、いいよ。
Nice, that's great.
で、リスナーも喜んでくれまして、この時に気づいたことがあります。次のページ。
And the listeners loved it too, which led me to realize something. Next page.
ホロライブには、ボケが多い。
There are too many boke in Hololive!
分かる～！そうだね
I totally get it! / Yeah, that's true.
そうなんですよ
Exactly.
ボケ属性のホロメンが非常に多いんです
There are so many Hololive members with "boke" attributes.
ということでね 僕はこうなります 次のページ
And so, I became this. Next page.
クセつよだらけのホロライブ「ツッコミ属性」に一筋の光！
A ray of light on the "tsukkomi attribute" in Hololive, which is full of eccentric characters!
おおー！
Ohh!
そうなんです 僕はここからツッコミについて学び出します
Exactly. From here, I started studying tsukkomi.
真面目に学び出しましてね
I studied it really seriously.
ツッコミできるようになったら 役割的にもいいのかなと思って
I thought if I could do tsukkomi, it would be great for my role in the group.
テレビを見て参考にしたツッコミ芸人の方がいらっしゃいます
And there's a tsukkomi comedian whom I watched on TV as a reference.
その方がこちら 次のページ
That person is here. Next page.
くりぃむしちゅーの上田晋也さん
Ueda Shinya of Cream Stew!
あ～！なるほど！確かに確かに！
Ah! I see! Definitely, definitely!
ツッコミだよね！ツッコミだね！
He is indeed a tsukkomi! / He is!
しゃべくり007とかを見て面白そうだなぁと思って
I was watching "Shabekuri 007" and thought, "This is so funny!"
上田さんを参考にツッコミを勉強しました
So I studied tsukkomi using Mr. Ueda as a reference.
例えツッコミが多くてすごく難しいんですけど
He does a lot of metaphorical tsukkomi, which is extremely difficult...
こんな風になりたいなと思いながら勉強いたしました
...but I studied while thinking, "I want to be like that."
もともと一方的に喋ってしまう オウム返しするみたいなことがあったけど
Originally, I would just talk unilaterally or just parrot things back...
ツッコミを意識してからは しっかり相手の言葉を聞いたり待つこともできるようになりました
...but once I became conscious of tsukkomi, I could properly listen to others and wait my turn.
すごい！素晴らしい！感動！
Wow! Wonderful! Touching!
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
こうして僕はツッコミで自分のポジションを開拓していくこととなります
And so, I went on to carve out my own position with tsukkomi.
ここまでの教訓としましては 次のページ
My lesson up to this point is... Next page.
自然とキャラはついてくる！焦って無理しても空回りするだけ！
Characters come naturally! If you rush and force it, you'll only spin your wheels!
なるほど～
I see~
無理してキャラ付けしなくても 勝手についていってその方が自分も楽だと
Even if you don't force a character persona, it will develop on its own, and that's easier on you.
配信の中で自然と自分に合ったキャラがついてくるのでね
A character that suits you will naturally develop through your streams.
焦らずホロメンと喋ったり 配信のいいやり方を見つけるのがいいんじゃないかと思います
So I think it's best not to rush, just talk with other members, and find a streaming style that works for you.
キャラをどうしようとか自分の理想もあるし 求められるものの違いとかあると思うんだけど
You might worry about your character or ideal, or feel different expectations, but...
一番やりやすいのが日々配信をたくさんするので絶対いいです
...doing what's most comfortable is absolutely best, since you'll stream a lot every day.
今「キャラ無い」とか思ってもいつか絶対ついていくから本当に大丈夫です
Even if you think "I have no character" right now, it will definitely come, so you'll be totally fine.
いや この配信マジで
Honestly, this stream is seriously...
全ホロライブの新人に見せる会やった方がいいですよ マジで
We should seriously have a viewing session of this for all new Hololive members.
間違いないよ まず入ったらこの配信を見てもらう
No doubt about it. As soon as they join, they should watch this stream.
とりあえず見ろって
Like, "just watch this first."
という感じで こうして配信にもだんだん慣れていった僕ですが
And so, as I gradually got used to streaming...
もともとホロライブに入ってやりたかったことがありました 次のページ
...there was something I originally wanted to do when I joined Hololive. Next page.
歌です
Singing.
おー歌ね イメージある ありがとうございます
Oh, singing. I can totally see that. / Thank you very much.
子供の頃からアイドルに憧れ続けておりまして
I've been admiring idols since I was a child.
パワーポイントデビュー配信でも「ライブでコール＆レスポンスするのが目標」と言っていたりします
And even in my PowerPoint debut stream, I said my goal was to do a call-and-response at a live concert.
当時は明確な目標はなく まぁ「いつかソロライブできたらな」っていう感じだったし
At the time, I didn't have a concrete goal, just a vague "I hope I can do a solo live someday" feeling.
そんなすぐにと等も思ってなかったです
And I didn't expect it to happen so soon either.
歌が大好きな僕は2020年の7月くらいから
And so, loving singing as I do, starting around July 2020...
月曜日の夜に毎週歌枠をやろうと思ってやってました
...I decided to do weekly singing streams on Monday nights.
いろんな方に歌聴いてほしいとか 歌上手くなりたいとかそういうことを思ってやってたので
I did it hoping many people would listen, and wanting to get better at singing...
自分でもすごく楽しみにしていた歌枠だったんですけど
...so it was a stream that I myself really looked forward to.
そんな僕に 異変が起きます
But then, an abnormality occurred.
なんだ？
What was it?
次のページ
Next page.
耳の持病が悪化
My chronic ear condition worsened.
そうなんですよ
That's right.
え、これ、どんな症状だったんでしたっけ？
Wait, what kind of symptoms did you have?
これはね デビュー前から高い音が聞こえにくいとか低音が聞こえにくいとか色々あったんですけど
Even before my debut, I had various issues, like finding it hard to hear high-pitched or low-pitched sounds.
もうこの頃はちょっと悪化しまして
But around this time, it worsened a bit...
片方の耳はほぼ聞こえてない
...and I could barely hear anything in one ear.
聞こえてないけど 常に耳鳴りがいつもしてたり
Even though I couldn't hear, I always had constant tinnitus...
何かの特定の音が割れて聞こえるような状態になっておりまして
...and certain specific sounds would sound distorted to me.
耳が聞こえづらいと 歌にどんな影響が出てしまうのか 次のページ
How does having trouble hearing affect your singing? Next page.
自分の歌声がわからない
I can't tell how my own singing voice sounds.
そうなんだ 大変だ
Oh, really? That's tough.
自分が歌ってる音程もちょっとズレて聞こえる時があるし
Sometimes the pitch of my own singing sounds off to me...
声の大きさがわからなくてなんか大きく出しちゃうんだよね 力んじゃう
...and since I can't tell how loud I am, I end up singing too loudly and straining myself.
うまく歌えなくてすごくこう難しい
I couldn't sing well, and it was extremely difficult.
となると あれだけ好きだった歌が嫌いになってくるんですよ
As a result, I started to dislike singing, which I used to love so much.
「うまく歌えないなぁ」ってなって 歌わないと...
Thinking "I can't sing well," and if I don't sing...
喉の筋肉も終わっていき どんどん下手になって「あぁ、もう嫌だ」と
...my vocal muscles started to weaken, making me even worse, and I felt like "Ugh, I hate this."
お医者さんからも「1回お休みした方がいいんじゃないか」と言われた結果 次のページ
And after my doctor suggested "Maybe you should take a break for once," the result was... Next page.
毎週やっていた歌枠が終了
The weekly singing streams came to an end.
悲しいよ
That's so sad...
悲しいとこなんですけどすごく悲しかったですね 歌にハンデがあるのはしょうがないと思いつつ
It's a really sad topic, and I felt deeply saddened. Though I knew having a singing handicap was unavoidable...
「なんでこういう自分なのかな」って落ち込んだ時期もありました
...there was a period when I felt depressed, wondering "Why am I like this?"
が、しかしそんな時に支えになったのがこちら 次のページ
However, what supported me during those times was this. Next page.
リスナーの温かい言葉と仲間のホロメン
The listeners' warm words and my fellow Holomem.
あったかい！
So heartwarming!
本当に助かりましたね やっぱりみんなに支えてもらって「時間がかかっても頑張ろう」と思えてきまして
Honestly, it really saved me. Being supported by everyone made me feel, "Even if it takes time, I'll keep trying."
どんどん上がっていきましたねモチベーション 歌も...
And my motivation steadily started to go back up. Even for singing...
よかった～！
Thank goodness!
本当にありがとうございます 一番大好きな音楽が嫌いになって趣味が1個なくなったって思ってたんですけど
Thank you all so much. I thought I had grown to hate my absolute favorite thing, music, and lost a hobby...
リスナーさんからは「それでも歌大好きだよ」って言ってもらえて
Listeners told me, "Even so, I still love your singing!"
「まだやっていいのかな」とか思えましたし
and it made me think, "Maybe it's okay for me to keep doing this..."
そういう風に今絶対聞き苦しいのに
Even though it must be hard to listen to right now,
聴いてくれるみんなのために頑張りたいと思いましたね
I felt I wanted to do my best for everyone who listens to me...
心から
...from the bottom of my heart.
やっぱりリスナーさんからのさ、温かい言葉ってさ、心に残るし嬉しいよね
Warm words from listeners really stay in your heart and make you happy, don't they?
嬉しい！そうそう、そうだよね
It makes us happy! Yeah, that's so true.
みんなあるよね、そういうことね
Everyone has had that kind of experience, right?
めっちゃあります！
I totally have!
ちょっとやっぱ落ち込んだときとかにエゴサして
When I'm feeling down and search my name,
「今日も可愛かったな」とか、「いっぱい頑張ってるね」とか
seeing comments like "She was cute today too," or "You're working so hard,"
そういう優しいコメント見るだけでもう胸がいっぱいになって、「また頑張ろう」って気持ちにマジでなれます
just seeing those kind comments fills my heart, and it honestly makes me feel like, "I'll do my best again!"
良いね
That's so nice.
ありがとう
Thank you!
そうだよね、素敵だね
Indeed. That's wonderful.
ラミィも自分の体調の悪化で
Lamy also had a period where I couldn't stream for a while
配信がしばらくできなかった時期があるんだけど
due to my health worsening,
その間にリスナーさんがずっと「ラミィちゃんいつまでも待ってるからね」「体調よく治すようにちゃんと今休むんだよ」って
and during that time, listeners kept saying, "Lamy-chan, we'll wait for you forever," "Rest well now so you can recover,"
ずっと待っててくれて
and they waited for me all that time.
実際復帰したときも、みんな温かく「ラミィちゃん待ってたよ、良かったね」って出迎えてくれて
When I actually returned, everyone welcomed me back so warmly, saying, "Lamy-chan, we were waiting for you, glad you're back!"
もう「リスナーさんあの時はありがとう、雪民さんいつも大好きだよ」って
I was like, "Listeners, thank you so much back then. Yukimin, I love you always!"
いい、エモい
That's so nice. Emotional.
おかゆ先輩もありますか？
Okayu-senpai, do you have any?
おかゆ先輩は体調崩したこととかはないけど
I haven't really gotten sick or anything, but...
やっぱりこう、ゲームやっててめっちゃ悲しいシーンが来て、えんえん泣いちゃったりして、鼻ずっびずびになったりするんだけど
when I'm playing a game and a really sad scene comes up, I'll cry my eyes out and my nose gets completely runny,
「ゆっくりでいいよ」「ゆっくり鼻かんでいいよ」って
but they tell me, "Take your time," "It's okay to blow your nose slowly."
言ってくれる優しさを感じますね、いつも本当に
I always feel their kindness when they say things like that, truly.
鼻かもう、鼻かもう。ありがとうね。優しいね、優しいね。
Blow your nose, blow your nose! Thank you. So kind.
あと、たくさんホロメンにも応援してもらって
Also, I got support from a lot of Holo-members too.
例えばフレア先輩から「耳の病気とかハンデがあっても、その上でも歌上手だからすごいよ！」って言ってもらったりして勇気づけられたりとか
For example, Flare-senpai told me, "Even with an ear disease or a handicap, you're still a great singer, so you're amazing!" which really encouraged me.
あとは同期の桐生ココというね、人がいたんですけれども
And then there was my genmate, Kiryu Coco.
まぁ、今卒業してしまいましたが、当時一緒の家で同居していたので
Well, she has graduated now, but we were living together in the same house back then,
僕が落ち込んでいる時、特に何か言うわけでもなく
so when I was feeling down, she didn't necessarily say anything special,
「あ、飯食う？」みたいな感じで
but she'd just be like, "Ah, wanna eat?"
ちょっと似てる、ちょっと似てる！「飯食う？」みたいな感じで。
That was a bit close! "Wanna eat?"
一緒にね、なんか味噌汁食べたりとか、午前３時におやつ食べたりとか
and we'd eat miso soup together, or have snacks at 3 AM.
そういうのができたのが、今思うとすごく助かりました
Looking back, being able to do things like that was a huge help.
そんな時に大事件が起きます保存
But then, a major incident occurred.
次のページ
Next page.
同期メンバーの「卒業」です。あああ...
A genmate's "graduation." Ah...
はい。これはですね、あの４期生は元々、今は４人なんですけど、５人おりまして
Yes. So, the 4th generation... well, there are four of us now, but originally there were five,
同期の天才のように面白かった桐生ココがですね、卒業することになりました
and my genmate Kiryu Coco, who was geniously funny, decided to graduate.
何より同居とかしてたりとか、生活を共にしたりっていうのもあって
Above all, since we were housemates and shared our daily lives,
色んな話も聞いていたし、仲もね、本当に一番良かったかなと思います
we talked about many things, and our bond was probably the closest.
その時に、活動の先に求めるものとか、生活の感じとかも色々似ていて、本当に気が合ったというか
At the time, what we sought in our activities and our lifestyles were very similar, so we really clicked.
そんなココの卒業っていうのは、僕にとってもかなり大きい出来事でございました
So Coco's graduation was an incredibly major event for me.
りりかはだって喋ったことないもんね
Ririka, you've never spoken to her, right?
そうですね、もうりりかが入ったときにはすでにご卒業されてたんですけど
That's right, she had already graduated by the time I joined,
「伝説のドラゴン」のイメージがすごくて、もう「最強の人」っていうイメージがあります
but she has this massive image of being a "legendary dragon," like the "strongest person."
いや、そうだよ。僕たち、ココちゃんとかかなたんの前から入ってるメンバーから見ても
Yeah, that's true. Even from the perspective of members like us who joined before Coco-chan and Kanatan,
やっぱココちゃんはすごい「伝説」を残していったなっていう印象はあります
Coco-chan really left behind an amazing "legend." That's the impression she left.
そうなんですよ。４期生がホロライブに入って、ARKとかね、あさココとかも毎日胸がドキドキするような時期だったし
That's right. When the 4th gen joined Hololive, with ARK and Asacoco, it was a time of daily excitement,
毎日の朝のライブ配信とか、他のホロメンの情報をまとめてニュースでやるっていうのがすごく斬新で
and her daily morning live streams, wrapping up other Holo-members' news, were so innovative.
天才だったなって保存
She was a genius.
本当そうですよね。準備とかも大変な中、そういうことをやって、箱のためになったらいいとすごく考える人でしたね保存
That's so true. Despite how hard preparation was, she did all that because she was always thinking about what's best for the agency.
そんな風に仲が良かったからこそ、卒業することが完全に決まった時は、やっぱり悲しい気持ちはもちろんありました
Because we were so close, when her graduation was officially decided, I naturally felt extremely sad.
で、その時にココの卒業を聞いた僕は、この時最後にやりたかったことがありました。それが、こちら次のページ。
And when I heard about Coco's graduation, there was one last thing I wanted to do. And that is... on the next page.
４期生としてのオリジナル楽曲
An original song as the 4th generation.
やっぱりせっかくなら５人のオリジナル曲欲しいよなって思ったんですよね
I thought, since we had this chance, I really wanted an original song for the five of us.
そこで運営さんに「４期生の曲作りたい！」と言うと、こう言われます。次のページ。
So when I told management, "I want to make a 4th gen song!", they said this. Next page.
「間に合いません。」あああ...
"We won't make it in time." "Ah..."
時間がね...
Time-wise...
そうなんですよね。曲の制作には時間かかりますし、卒業が決まった時にはもう「今からの楽曲制作は間に合わない」とはっきり言われました
Indeed. Song production takes time, so when her graduation was decided, they plainly told me, "Starting song production now won't make it in time."
これを言われた僕はこう思います。次のページ。
Hearing this, here's what I thought. Next page.
「だったら自分で作っちゃおう！」
"Then I'll just make it myself!"
おおー！すごい！よくそうなった！
Oh! Amazing! How did you end up doing that?!
やっぱり外注すると間に合わないなら、
If outsourcing it wouldn't make it in time...
はい。っていうことがあるなら、自分で作ればね、間に合うだろう、と思って...
Yes. I figured if that's the case, if I write it myself, it'll make it in time...
ま、初めての作詞作曲をします。
And so, I wrote lyrics and composed a song for the first time.
こうしてできた楽曲が次のページ！
And the song that came out of that is on the next page!
4th期生5人で歌う最初で最後のオリジナル楽曲「キセキ結び」となります。
It's the first and last original song sung by the five 4th generation members: "Kiseki Musubi".
当時ね、当時の僕が思いを込めて、
I poured all my feelings into it back then,
いろんな方に協力していただいて完成し、発表することができました。
and thanks to the cooperation of many people, we were able to complete and release it.
映像があるんでご覧ください。
We have the video here, so please take a look.
約束しようよ 僕ら出会えたキセキ
Let's make a promise about the miracle of our meeting,
忘れないように
so that we will never forget it.
夢抱いて集う 青春アニメみたいな
We gather holding onto dreams, like a youth anime,
ハッピーエンドになる 彼方へと跳ぶよ
flying toward the far-off happy ending.
寝ぼけ目あくびして 今日は何をしようか？
Yawning with sleepy eyes, what should we do today?
永久に続く海を 駆け抜ける
We will run across the eternally stretching sea.
今はため息 よりも勇気を
Right now, choose courage over sighing.
諦めるなんてないの ここで歌う
There's no giving up, we will sing right here.
僕の
My...
声は聞こえてますか？ 君に届け
...voice, can you hear it? Let it reach you!
学校の友達じゃ きっとない出会いだった
This was a meeting we'd never have as school friends.
画面の先の遥か遠くまで
To the far-off place beyond the screen.
ささくれた言葉も 誰かの笑顔になる
Even splintered words can make someone smile.
それぞれの色で 星結ぶキセキ
A miracle of tying stars together in our own colors.
キラキラ輝くステージに
To the glittering, shining stage...
連れてくよ
...I will take you!
はい！ありがとうございましたー！
Yes! Thank you so much!
めっちゃよかったー！
That was so good!
ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
いや、本当にこれメロディも歌詞もよくて、本当に...
No, seriously, both the melody and lyrics are so good...
この曲を作っていた当時、おかゆ先輩とめっちゃ遊んでて、
When I was writing this song, I hung out with Okayu-senpai all the time.
めっちゃ遊んでたよね。毎日会ってたよね。
We hung out so much! We saw each other every day, right?
その時かなたんが「僕今作詞頑張ってて」って言ってたよね。
Back then, Kanatan told me, "I'm working hard on the lyrics right now."
それで完成した曲がこんなに良い曲だからさ！
And the song that came out of it is just so wonderful!
すっごい褒めてくれて、本当に。
You praised me so much, really. Thank you.
歌詞の中にみんなの名前が入ってるって、エモエモすぎんか？
Having everyone's name in the lyrics is just way too touching, isn't it?!
エモいよ、本当に。
It's so emotional, honestly.
天才でしょこれ。
You're a genius for doing this.
いやいや、本当にいろんな人に助けていただいて。
No, no, I really had help from so many people.
こうしてね、ココを送り出すことになったんですけれど...
And so, we ended up sending Coco off, but...
悲しんだりとか、寂しがってるだけではいけないと、思いました。
I realized we can't just be sad or feeling lonely forever.
この頃の人生グラフはこうなっております。次のページ！
My life graph around this time looked like this.
次のページ。
Next page!
お、上がってきた！
Oh, it's going up!
上がったー！
It went up!
上がってきたんです。周りと比較するより、
It went up. Rather than comparing yourself to others,
過去の自分と比較するっていうのが一番いいよね、とココと話していて。
it's best to compare yourself to your past self. Coco and I often talked about that.
そういうことを続けて、とにかく自分を磨いていこうと思いました。
I decided to keep doing that and focus on polishing myself.
改めて歌に力を入れていくんですが、
From then, I put my efforts back into singing,
ソロライブをやるにはどうすればいいか？と考えた時に、
and when I thought about what it takes to do a solo live concert,
まずは「天音かなた＝歌」という、
firstly, to establish the association of "Amane Kanata = Singing",
そういう印象をつけようと思いました。
I wanted to engrain that impression.
そのために意識していたことがあります。次のページ。
To do that, there was something I kept in mind. Next page.
他のメンバーのライブに多数ゲスト出演！
Appearing as a guest on many other members' live concerts!
記念ライブにホロメンをゲストで呼ぶのが当たり前の時代だったので、
Since we were in an era where inviting Holomem guests was common,
頂いたオファーも本当にありがたい機会として、お祝いする気持ちが一番ですが、
I treated every offer as a grateful opportunity, with celebrating them being my top priority.
自分ももっと歌いたい、成長したいという思いで、オファーを片っ端から引き受けました。
But also with my desire to sing more and grow, I accepted the offers one after another.
さらに、こんなことをしてみます。次のページ。
In addition to that, I tried doing this. Next page.
2周年記念ライブで、ゲストなしのソロライブ！
A solo concert with zero guests for my 2nd anniversary live!
やましたね。
We did that, didn't we?
このデビュー2周年記念ライブ「リベンジ」では、
In this debut 2nd anniversary concert, "Revenge",
ゲストを呼ぶのが当然の中で、ソロライブをする人がいなくなっていたのですが、
while inviting guests was the norm, almost no one was doing solo-only lives anymore.
あえてゲストを呼ばず、1時間で15曲も、
I intentionally did not invite guests, and in just one hour,
歌うライブに挑戦的にやってみたりもしました。
I took on the challenge of singing 15 songs in total.
この頃から自分の歌について真剣に向き合うようになりますが、
So from around this time, I began to face my own singing seriously.
一から発声や歌い方を見直すことになります。
And I ended up re-evaluating my vocalization and singing style from scratch.
ここでやったことがこちら。次のページ。
Here is what I did. Next page.
自分の歌い方の「癖」の選別、人気曲のボーカル抽出分析、昔の曲の研究...
Identifying the habits in my singing style, extracting and analyzing vocals of popular songs, studying old songs...
気になることがいっぱいある！
There are so many interesting things on that list!
気になる。
I'm curious.
歌い方の「癖」の選別ってなに？
What exactly is "identifying the habits in your singing style"?
この癖なんですけど
Speaking of these habits...
強い癖があったほうが個性があっていいとか
Some say a strong habit is good for individuality...
癖がないほうが聞きやすいよとか
...while others say having no habits makes it easier to listen to.
あったんですけど
That's what people said,
まずは自分はやっぱり癖はどちらかというと強いから
but since my habits are on the stronger side,
じゃあどこを残そうかと
I thought, "Which ones should I keep?"
いうのを考えたときに
When I was thinking about that,
まずは癖をゼロにしようと思いまして
I decided to start by reducing my habits to zero.
あの ちょうど「炉心融解」とかボーカロイドの曲を歌ったんですけど
For instance, when I covered Vocaloid songs like "Meltdown",
そのときは癖ゼロで、ボカロみたいに歌うことを意識したりしました
I made a conscious effort to sing with zero habits, just like a Vocaloid.
いい癖は残して
Keep the good habits,
ちょっと聞きにくいなっていう癖はなるべくなくす
and eliminate the ones that make it hard to listen to.
っていうことで、ちょっとブラッシュアップをしていこうと思ってましたね
I wanted to brush up my singing that way.
いや でも思った 一時期のときからかなたんの歌い方変わったなって思った
But now that I think about it, I did feel Kanata's singing style changed at one point.
あ そうなんです おかゆ先輩ともね いっぱい歌ってみたね 歌わせていただいてるんですけど
Ah, that's right. I've done many covers with you too, Okayu-senpai.
初期の頃 歌ってみたやってる時はまだ選別前で
But back in my early days, before I started sorting them out,
ちょっとブスのとき
my voice was a bit "ugly."
ちょいブスのときね
The "slightly ugly" phase.
そういうこともあった
Yes, there was a phase like that.
みたいに感じで
Something like that.
ただ これは結構辛い作業で
But this was a pretty painful process.
これは実は1年かかりまして
It actually took me a whole year.
選びましたね
I carefully selected them.
あと人気曲の 例えば
And for popular songs, like...
YOASOBIさんとかの流行りのアーティスト
...trending artists like YOASOBI.
やっぱ流行りの歌い方っていうものがあるなっていうのを感じて
I felt there's a certain "trendy" way of singing.
あの そういう方々のボーカルを聞いて
So I listened to their vocals,
こういう癖は入れるけど ここにはこれはいれないだとか
and decided, "I'll use this habit here, but not that one there."
そういうのを研究というか分析しましたね
I researched and analyzed things like that.
勉強熱心や
So studious!
流行りがありつつも
While following the trends,
寄せるか寄せまいかっていうのはすごくね 考えましたね
I thought hard about whether to mimic them or not.
あとは 昔の歌も研究して
I also researched older songs.
曲にも こう 流行りの周期があって
Every song has its trend cycle.
ロックっぽいのが流行ったり バラードが流行ったりとか
Like when rock-style is popular, or ballads are in...
今はこう ちょっとエモ系だったり
...and now it's more "emo" style.
この昔流行った曲とかそのときに流行ってる歌い方
I did a lot of research on songs that were popular in the past
とかもかなり研究を
and the singing styles of those times.
すごい！
Amazing!
なんか さっきツッコミも その色々
Earlier, we talked about you studying how to do comebacks...
勉強されてたみたいな話もあったし 今回もこう 色々研究して
...and this time you've researched so much too.
本当に努力家というか
You're really a hard worker.
ありがとう 120点のコメント
Thank you for the perfect 120-point comment!
え？
Huh?
とにかくこれほどしないと 自分の耳の件もありますし
Anyway, if I didn't go this far, especially with my hearing issues,
ちょっと聞きづらくなってる歌っていうのが なかなか変えられないなってことで
I felt I couldn't easily fix parts of my singing that were hard to listen to.
一からやろうと思って
So I decided to start from scratch.
これをやった結果 昔3時間かかっていたレコーディングが
As a result, recording that used to take 3 hours...
今は20分くらいで終わるようになりました
...now finishes in about 20 minutes!
すごーい！はやーい！
Amazing! So fast!
これもね レコーディングをやるときに
When I used to record,
この癖を入れたいなって何度も何度も試すとかやってたんですけど
I used to try repeatedly to fit a specific habit in.
それが やっぱり パッとできるようになった
But now, I can just do it instantly.
納得できる歌い方ができるようになったっていう感じでしたね
I can sing in a way I'm satisfied with right away.
みなさんはレコーディングにこだわりってありますか？
Do you all have any specific preferences when recording?
こだわりというか
Well, rather than a preference...
今現在
right now,
まさに自分の癖で悩んでて
I'm actually struggling with my own habits.
なんか 歌って今までやってこなかったんだけど
I hadn't really sung much before,
ホロライブに入って 歌を歌う機会がすごく増えて
but since joining Hololive, my opportunities to sing have increased so much.
初めて自分の癖みたいなのが出てきちゃってるの 逆に
And on the contrary, my own habits have started showing up for the first time.
それを残したほうがいいのか
Should I keep those habits,
省いてもっと まっさらな歌い方にしたらいいのか
or eliminate them and aim for a completely clean style?
すごい今リアルタイムで悩んでて
I'm seriously struggling with this in real-time.
この件かなたんに相談します
I'll have to consult Kanata about this.
待ってます！
I'll be waiting!
二人は？
What about you two?
マリンは なんか感情が死んでるのか分かんないんですけど
For me, I don't know if my emotions are just dead, but...
どういうこと？
What do you mean?
歌うときに 感情を乗せるのがあんまり得意じゃなくて
When singing, I'm not very good at conveying emotion.
歌詞の意味とかが 頭をスーって通り抜けちゃうんです
The meaning of the lyrics just passes straight through my head.
なるべくどういう情景かとかを思い描きながら歌うように頑張ってるんで
So I try my best to visualize the scene while singing.
まずは ちょっと感情を取り戻すところから
So first, I need to start by recovering my emotions. My emotions are gone?!
なくなってる！？化け物かもしれない
They're gone?! She might be a monster!
そんなことはない
That's not true!
おかゆ先輩 感情入れて歌うの逆に得意な気がしますけど
Okayu-senpai, on the other hand, you seem really good at emotional singing.
ほんと？
Really?
僕とかかなたんってさ
For people like Kanata and me,
ミックスの勉強もしてたことあったじゃん
we also studied mixing, right?
だから ミックスするとどうしても表情感って消えやすい
And when you mix, the emotional expression tends to fade easily.
ピッチの補正でね
With pitch correction, yeah.
補正で消えるんだよ
Pitch correction wipes it out.
だから ピッチをとるか表現をとるか考えること多いかもね
So we often have to choose between perfect pitch and pure expression.
大事やな
That is important.
そう 音程を気にするとやっぱり表情が落ちていくっていうのは絶対あるから
Right, focusing too much on pitch definitely drags down the emotion.
この1行めっちゃいいから ここだけ入れようとか決めるとやりやすい
It's easier if you decide, "This line is amazing, so I'll put maximum emotion here."
めっちゃ勉強になる！
That's so helpful!
と言いつつ 僕もまだまだなんですけど こういった地道な活動の結果
Though I'm still learning too. But as a result of these steady efforts...
2022年の年末に行われた 3周年記念ライブ「別世界」ではこうなります 次のページ
At my 3rd anniversary live 'Another World' in late 2022, this happened. Next page!
21秒のロングトーン、歌が大反響！
The 21-second long-tone song was a massive hit!
ありがとうございます
Thank you so much!
このライブでのロングトーン部分の映像があるみたいなので
It seems we have video of the long-tone part of this live stream,
よろしければご覧ください、どうぞ！
so please take a look if you'd like. Go ahead!
おお！
Oh!
ショートとかでもめっちゃ流れてくるからね
Because it shows up on Shorts all the time.
そうなんだよね
That's true.
そうそう
Yeah, yeah.
僕じゃない人がショートたくさん切り抜いてる
Many people who are not me are clipping it for Shorts.
そうそう、すごいからね
Yeah, because it's amazing.
脅威の、みたいな
Like, "The Menace of..."
何回も見たい、ここ
I want to watch this part over and over.
始まる、始まる
It's starting, it's starting.
やばい、もう息した？
Oh my god, did she breathe yet?
そうそう、息した、息した。もう息したい、息したい
Yeah, she breathed. I want to breathe, I want to breathe.
もう喉苦しい、喉苦しい
My throat hurts, my throat hurts.
こっから、上がるのがすごいの！
From here, going up is what's amazing!
本当に！？上がる！？
Really?! Going up?!
どうやって！？マジでやばい
How?! This is seriously insane.
え、最後のビブラートね
And that last vibrato.
うん
Yeah.
まだ残ってるじゃん！ってなる
You're like, "She's still holding it?!"
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
すごい技術だよ、これ
Wow, that's an amazing technique.
いやいやいや、とんでもなく練習したんですけども
No, no, no, I practiced like crazy, but...
あの、これは実は元をたどると、ちょっと逃げのロングトーンで
Actually, if you trace it back, it was a bit of an "escape" long tone.
ええ！？
What?!
どこに逃げたの？
Where did you escape to?
あの、この「unravel」という楽曲、ここでデスボイスが本家だと
In the original song "unravel", there is a death growl here,
「ヴッーー、おあーー」って出るの
like, "Vaaaaah!!"
それができないんでロングトーンにした
Since I couldn't do that, I made it a long tone.
えぇ！？
What?!
っていうのが、実ははじめだったんです
That was actually how it started.
逃げではない！逃げてない、挑戦だよ！
That's not escaping! You're not escaping, it's a challenge!
デスボイスから逃げてきて、ロングトーンと、なったんですが
I escaped from the death growl and ended up with a long tone, but...
やりたいことをかなり詰め込んだライブが成功して
The live show where I packed in a lot of what I wanted to do was a success,
100万人記念の新衣装も見せるタイミングだったり
and it was also the timing to show my 1 million subscriber commemorative new outfit,
unravelではロングトーンしたことを、思った以上にいろんな方に見ていただいて
and many more people than I expected watched the long tone in "unravel",
「今までで1番ライブよかった！」っていう反響をいただいたりとか
and I received feedback like, "It was the best live show ever!"
「歌上手くなったね」って言ってもらえるのがすごく嬉しくて、まだ頑張っていこうと思いました
I was so happy to hear people say, "You've gotten better at singing," that I decided to keep doing my best.
この時の反響がなければ、今自分はね、必死に歌頑張るということはなかったかなと思います
If it wasn't for the response at that time, I don't think I would be working so hard on my singing now.
で、そのあとね、去年3月に天音かなたファーストアルバムCDの「Unknown DIVA」を発表することもできまして
And after that, in March last year, I was able to release Amane Kanata's first album CD, "Unknown DIVA".
見事完売できまして
And it sold out completely!
おお、素晴らしい！すごい！
Oh, wonderful! Amazing!
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
運営さんもね、頑張ったと認めてくれたのかなっていう風に感じましたし
I felt that the management also recognized my hard work,
何より聴いたへい民のみんなが嬉しそうにしてくれたり、好きな曲を発見してくれたりしてすごく嬉しかったます
and above all, I was so happy that all the Heimin (listeners) seemed happy and discovered songs they liked.
そしてなんと！
And also!
今年7月23日には！
On July 23rd of this year!
なにこの動き？
What is this movement?
セカンドアルバム「Trigger」を発売します！
We will release the second album "Trigger"!
さらにさらに、
Furthermore,
8月13日は、待望のソロライブを行わせていただくことになりました！
on August 13th, I will be holding my long-awaited solo live concert!
おめでとう！すごい！
Congratulations! Amazing!
ありがとうございます。ありがとうございます
Thank you very much. Thank you very much.
このアルバムのTriggerは、ジャケットとかアナザージャケットっていうのを自分で発注からやって
For this album "Trigger", I handled everything from ordering the jacket and alternative jackets myself,
クオリティにこだわっていたりとか
focusing heavily on quality,
楽曲なんですけど、「十万億土」という楽曲をね、作詞作曲してみました
and as for the music, I wrote the lyrics and composed a song called "Juman-okudo".
ラップを入れてみたり挑戦してみたので、ぜひチェックしてほしいです
I challenged myself with things like adding rap, so please check it out.
めっちゃ楽しみー
Looking forward to it!
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
他にも「世界で一番のアイドル」という楽曲の作詞もしまして
I also wrote the lyrics for another song called "Sekai de Ichiban no Idol" (The World's Number One Idol),
こちらはですね、先ほどの「十万億土」とは全く違く
and this one is completely different from "Juman-okudo".
もう素直な気持ちを…韻などは踏んでおりません！
Just my honest feelings... I didn't write any rhymes!
素直な気持ちを文字にしたので、応援してくれるへい民に届いたらいいなと思っております
I put my honest feelings into words, so I hope it reaches the Heimin who support me.
絶対届くよ！
It will definitely reach them!
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
全体的に歌がパワーアップしていると思いますので、ソロライブを楽しみにしていてほしいと思います！
I think my singing has leveled up overall, so please look forward to the solo concert!
そんな僕の現在のホロライブ人生グラフはこうなります。次のページ！
And this is my current Hololive life graph. Next page!
おお、上がってる！上がってる！上昇してる！
Wow, it's going up! It's going up! It's rising!
現在右肩上がりで順調にいかさせていただいております
Currently, it's steadily rising, and things are going smoothly.
おお、すごい！
Oh, amazing!
ここにつ集まってくれた3人、本当に僕は心から感謝していて
And all of this is thanks to the three of you who gathered here today. I truly appreciate you from the bottom of my heart,
忙しい中来てもらって…
for coming despite your busy schedules...
カニが待っているからな
Because crab is waiting for us.
カニ食べたい！カニ食べたい！カニ！カニ！
I want to eat crab! I want to eat crab! Crab! Crab!
奢りたいと思います
I would like to treat you all.
最後に僕のデビュー配信を振り返らせていただきますが、僕はデビュー配信でこんなことを言っていました。こちら
Lastly, let's look back at my debut stream. I said something like this during my debut stream. Here it is.
なんかさ、僕が初配信でこうやっていっぱい話したさ
You know, in my first stream, I talked a lot about...
あの、突拍子もない夢を、いつか叶えることができたら、それはまず
if I can ever make those wild dreams come true, first of all,
リスナーさん、へい民の皆さんのおかげだから
it will be thanks to my listeners, the Heimin,
こうして活動が始まったけど、最初から最後まで頑張って、自分も皆も今より幸せになるようにって
since my activities started like this, I want to do my best from start to finish, so both you and I can be happier than we are now.
それが天音かなたがVTuberとして活動する理由です
That is Amane Kanata's reason for active duty as a VTuber.
これ、初配信でしてんの？
Did I really say this on my debut stream?
いろんなしくじりや事件があって紆余曲折しましたが、
Although we went through various failures, incidents, and twists and turns...
今こうして天音かなたという僕が出来上がりました。ありがとうございます。
...here I am today, fully formed as Amane Kanata. Thank you so much.
今日の授業いかがだったでしょうか？
How was today's lesson, everyone?
めっちゃ良かったよ。
It was really great!
超勉強になった。
I learned so much!
かなたんが努力の人って、この時間でものすごい分かったと思う。
I think we really saw during this lesson that Kanatan is a hard worker.
本当にありがとう。
Thank you so much.
いろんな苦労もあっただろうに、それを感じさせず...
Even though she went through so much trouble, she never lets it show...
いやいやいや、本当にね、僕は正直、この授業をホロメン全員分見たいぐらいあります。
No, no... Honestly, I want to see a lesson like this for every single Holomem.
みんなの人生を教えてくれ、と。いうことでね、歌の話もして、
Like, "Tell me about your lives!" So, now that we've talked about the song, too...
ちょっと実はね、まあ、はっきり言ってこれはね、みなさん、収録なんです。はっきり言って。
Actually... to be completely honest, everyone, this is a pre-recording. Frankly speaking.
はっきり言って収録だから、僕たち今、過去から来ています。
Since it's pre-recorded, we are currently talking to you from the past.
未来の僕、今ここから生で続きの配信してくるので、
My future self is about to do a live stream continuing from this, so...
じゃあ、未来に行ってくる！
Well then, I'm heading to the future!
えっ、置いていかれる感じ？私たちはこのあとどうしたら？
Wait, are we being left behind? What are we supposed to do now?
カニ行こうな！
Let's go eat crab!
いぇーい！カニ！
Yay! Crab!
行ってくる〜！未来に！
I'm off to the future!
手詰まりな現状の行き場が とめどない感情と交差する
The dead-end state of affairs intersects with endless emotions.
どうしたってもう変えられない それはきっと個人の過護じゃない
No matter what, it can't be changed anymore; surely it's not due to individual fault.
セルフ手助けが利くのは 限られた範囲の話で
Self-help only works within a limited range,
そこから先は不可干渉 どうしたって何をしたって勝機がないんだって
beyond that, it's non-interference; no matter what you do, there's no chance of winning.
自分がどう足掻こうと びくともしない机上の仮説
No matter how I struggle, this academic hypothesis won't budge.
それならこれからの方法も 知らないからね
In that case, I don't even know how to proceed from here.
変わらない後悔があったとて 今できることなんて何もないんだ
Even if there are unchanging regrets, there is absolutely nothing I can do now.
動いたところで救えはしない 決まりきった事実に降す理想もない
Even if I act, it won't save us; there's no ideal that can override a foregone conclusion.
丁寧な暮らしをしていても 最善ってやつに手が届かなかった
Even if I live a meticulous life, the "best outcome" was still out of reach.
いろんなものを捨てていくだろう そして徐々に心が軽くなってしまう
I'll probably end up casting away various things, and gradually my heart will grow lighter.
認め切れない言葉の連鎖で きっと僕らは無力であった
With a chain of words we can't fully accept, we were surely powerless.
事情の行方が定まらないなら いっそ何もわからないままだ
If the direction of events remains uncertain, we might as well know nothing at all.
治まりきれない常識の尺度は 絶対的に正しくないが
The scale of common sense that cannot be contained is absolutely not correct, but...
僕の手におえない君の脳裏は どうやっても救えやしない
Your mind, which is beyond my control, cannot be saved no matter what I do.
君らが自愛を乞うたって 正直役目の管轄外
Even if you beg for self-love, honestly, it's outside my jurisdiction.
結局未来の想定も セルフとなってます
Ultimately, even future assumptions are completely self-service.
しょうもない救済を待ってても 神様も使いはよこしてこないし
Even if you wait for worthless salvation, God won't send an emissary,
時間が調子すぎるだけ とめどない思考事情も知らず
time just passes by favorably, without knowing your endless train of thought.
変わらない後悔があったとて 今できることなんて何もないんだ
Even if there are unchanging regrets, there is absolutely nothing I can do now.
動いたところで救えはしない 決まりきった事実に降す理想もない
Even if I act, it won't save us; there's no ideal that can override a foregone conclusion.
十人十色関係なく 今自分のことで精一杯なんだ
Regardless of our differences, I have my hands completely full with my own issues right now.
空を飛ぶための羽もないが 地に足つけて歩むしかないのだろう
I don't have wings to fly through the sky, so I suppose I have no choice but to walk with my feet on the ground.
みんなー！
Everyone!
見ましたか？帰ってきたよ。ちょっと、この教室誰も...
Did you see it? I'm back. Wait, there's no one in this classroom...
はっ！ちょっと一回息整...誰もいない！
*Phew* Let me catch my breath... No one's here!
おい、本当に帰った！
Hey, they really went home!
いや、ありがとうございました。
Well, thank you very much.
ということで、すごい高かったよね？
By the way, the pitch was really high, wasn't it?
パチパチありがとう！
Thank you for the claps!
今、歌った曲なんですが、新曲になります！
The song I just sang is actually my brand new song!
こちら、7月23日水曜日に発売予定の僕のセカンドアルバム『Trigger』から、サツキさんに制作いただいた『セルフサービス』を初披露させていただきました。
Today, I premiered "Self Service," a track from my second album "Trigger" releasing on Wed, July 23rd, produced by Satsuki-san.
本日、このあと21時からMVを公開、そして24時から各配信サービスにて音源リリース予定です！そして！
The MV will drop today at 21:00, and the single will be released on streaming services at 24:00! And!
アルバム追加情報として、『Trigger』に収録されている全9曲の情報を...
As additional album news, here is the information for all 9 tracks included in "Trigger"...
初公開！
First reveal!
今回も超豪華作家陣の皆様に素敵な全9曲作っていただきました！
Once again, an incredibly stellar lineup of creators has made 9 wonderful songs!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
アルバムはアクスタ3種セットや限定ホロカードが入っている超豪華な完全生産限定盤、
The album comes in a super deluxe Complete Limited Edition containing 3 acrylic stands and a limited holo card,
そしてA、Bの2形態をご用意している通常盤の計3種が...
and the Regular Edition available in two types, A and B, making three types in total...
大大、大好評！と、言っておきますからね、みんなよろしくお願いします！
...which are highly, highly acclaimed! (Or so I claim, please support it, everyone!)
ご予約受付中ですので、ぜひぜひ手に入れてくださいね！
Pre-orders are now open, so please make sure to grab yours!
そしてね、YouTubeご覧の皆様、
And for those watching on YouTube,
配信画面の下にタグ付けされている商品の購入ボタンから
you can pre-order from the product purchase button tagged right below the stream screen,
ご予約できますのでチェックしてください、絶対！
so please check it out without fail!
頑張って設定したから、多分いるはず！
I worked hard setting it up, so they should definitely be there!
そして！皆さん、お待ちかね！
And now, everyone, the moment you've been waiting for!
ホロライブの追加の告知でございます！
An additional announcement from Hololive!
まずは...おお、ありがとうね。
First... Oh, thank you.
まずはこちらの動画をどうぞ！
First, please check out this video!
2025.8.13
[On-Screen: 2025.8.13]
Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live
[On-Screen: Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live]
狙いを定めたその先は、あなたの心 ――
[On-Screen: My sights are set on... your heart—]
楽曲一発一発に
[On-Screen: Into every single song,]
僕の“感情”を込めて
[On-Screen: I pour my "emotions"...]
全力で撃ち抜いていく
[On-Screen: and shoot with all my might.]
Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live LOOK ON
[On-Screen: Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live: LOCK ON]
8.13 Wed. ARIAKE ARENA
[On-Screen: 8.13 Wed. ARIAKE ARENA]
一人ひとりの感情に、確かな共鳴（トリガー）が広がっていく
[On-Screen: Within each person's emotions, a definite trigger resonates.]
かっこいいーー！！ということで！
That was so cool!! And with that...
今回のライブタイトルは、「天音かなた 1st ソロライブ 『LOCK ON』」です！
the title of this live concert is "Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live 'LOCK ON'"!
セカンドアルバム『Trigger』との繋がりも考えて、
Thinking of its connection to my second album "Trigger,"
ライブでみんなをね、ガンガン撃ち抜いていくイメージでございます！
the concept is about shooting down all of your hearts!
キービジュアルは、現実世界に天界の門が降臨した、
The key visual depicts a celestial gate descending into the real world,
異世界感のある雰囲気になってます。どうですか？
creating an otherworldly atmosphere. What do you think?
このクールでかっこいい僕を見て、ライブへの期待感、爆上がり？
Seeing me looking this cool, did your anticipation skyrocket?
有明アリーナもね！皆さん、お待たせしました！
And yes, Ariake Arena! Everyone, sorry to keep you waiting!
会場は有明アリーナで開催いたします！
The venue will be Ariake Arena!
本当にね、たくさんのホロライブの先輩たちも、
So many of my Hololive seniors
こちらでね、ライブをやってきているので、頑張ろうと思います！
have held concerts here, so I will do my absolute best!
今回のソロライブのハッシュタグはですね、「#撃ち抜けかなた」です！
The hashtag for this solo concert is "#撃ち抜けかなた" (#ShootDownKanata)!
どんどんみんなポストして、一緒にライブを盛り上げてくれーー！
Post as much as you can, and let's pump up the hype together!
そして！じゃじゃん！チケット情報は、こちら！
And, ta-dah! Here is the ticket information!
S席、A席、B席の3種類をご用意いたしました！
We have three types of seats available: S, A, and B seats!
1次先行は、この後21時から申し込み開始となります！
First-round pre-orders will start right after this at 9:00 PM!
これね、抽選なんで、みんな慌てずに、大丈夫ですからね。
It's a lottery, so please take your time and don't panic.
今回は、チケット販売サイトの「ZAIKO」で、
This time, on the ticket sales site "ZAIKO,"
海外のへい民向けにも現地チケットを販売します！
we will also sell venue tickets for overseas Heimin!
世界中のね、へい民に会えるの、楽しみにしてるからね、みんな！
I'm so looking forward to meeting Heimin from all over the world!
会場には、おら、行けないよ！って人も、全然大丈夫！
For those who can't make it to the venue, no worries at all!
配信チケットは、「SPWN」と「ZAIKO」で販売します！
Streaming tickets will be sold on SPWN and ZAIKO!
こちらも21時から販売開始なので、配信でね、ぜひ僕の勇姿を見に来てください！
These also go on sale at 9:00 PM, so please watch my performance on the stream!
各学生、あ、間違えたわ。各座席のエリアマップは、こちら！
And for each student... wait, I misspoke. Each seat's area map is right here!
S席は1階と3階前方、A席は1階後方と2階、B席は3階後方と4階に分かれています。
S seats are 1F & front of 3F; A seats are back of 1F & 2F; B seats are back of 3F & 4F.
お前らいっぱいね、いっぱい来てね、散らばってくれ！
Come in huge numbers and spread out everywhere!
そして、みんなお待ちかねのグッズ情報もあります！
And next, here is the merchandise info you've all been waiting for!
グッズもね、この後21時より販売開始するんで、
The merchandise will also go on sale starting at 9:00 PM,
まずはライブに欠かせない、応援セットをご紹介！じゃじゃん！
so first, let's introduce the essential Concert Support Set! Ta-dah!
きちゃー！
It's here!
うぱおライトは、見た目の通り、うぱおがモチーフになりました！
As you can see, the Upao Light is designed after Upao!
お前らもずっとほしいって言ってたもんね、ライブ会場をうぱおで埋め尽くしましょう！
You guys kept saying you wanted one, so let's fill the venue with Upao!
Tシャツは、今回のライブタイトルにある「LOCK ON」にちなんで、
For the T-shirt, inspired by the "LOCK ON" title of this concert,
胸に照準マークをね、モチーフにプリントしてみました！
we printed a crosshair motif on the chest!
みんなのね、あの心臓、僕が思いっきり撃ち抜いてあげますので、
I will completely shoot through all of your hearts,
ぜひ天界に遊びにきてください、ライブでもぜひ着てください！
so please come visit our celestial realm, and wear it at the live!
フェイスタオルは、ロゴを大きくあしらったデザインになっていて、
The face towel features a design with a large logo,
これもね、弾丸で撃ち抜かれたイメージでかっこいいので、
and this bullet-ridden concept looks super cool too!
お前らもね、みんなTシャツと一緒に身につけてくれたら嬉しいなと思います！
I'd be so happy if you all wear it together with the T-shirt!
セット特典のラバーバンドは、クリア素材で涼しげなデザイン、
The rubber band set-exclusive bonus has a cool, clear material design,
ロゴが入った特別仕様なので、みんなぜひゲットしてね、内側にあの、「COVER」って書いてありました！
with a special logo. Make sure to get it! By the way, "COVER" is written on the inside!
それぞれのグッズは単品でも販売します！
Each item will also be sold individually!
他の先行グッズは、こちら！じゃん！
And here is the other advance merchandise! Ta-dah!
リングライトとハッピも、先行発送対象となります！
The ring light and happi coat are also eligible for early shipping!
ハッピほしかったでしょ？
You guys really wanted a happi, didn't you?
リングライトにもね、「ここ撃ち抜いて」ってアピールできるように、照準アイコン入れてみました！
I also put a crosshair icon on the ring light so you can appeal with a "shoot here" sign!
へい民のみんな、僕がね、どんどん、どんどんお前らを撃ち抜いていくので、ぜひライブで光らせてください！
I'm going to shoot down all of you Heimin, one by one, so please light it up at the concert!
ハッピは背面にキービジュアルのかなたを大きくあしらいました！
The back of the happi features a large print of Kanata's key visual!
キービジュアルの雰囲気に合わせて、ちょっと...
To match the vibe of the key visual, it's slightly...
サイバーチックなデザインにもしてもらいましたが
We got a cyber-themed design for this,
ソーラン節もちょっと浮かぶよね
but it also kind of reminds you of Soran Bushi, doesn't it?
みんなお前ら当然フル装備で
Everyone, of course you'll gear up
応援してくれるよね？
fully to support me, right?
リングライトとハッピは応援セットには実は含まれませんので
The ring light and happi coat are actually not in the support set,
この辺ね、あの、注意してくださいね。そして
so please watch out for that. And...
受注販売グッズはこちら！
here are the made-to-order goods!
じゃじゃん！
Ta-da!
これ、トートバッグがすごい良かった、サンプル見たんですけど
This tote bag is awesome, I saw the sample.
トートバッグはね、痛バッグとしても使えるように缶バッジ飾れる透明のポケットがついてて
It can be used as an "ita-bag" since it has a clear pocket to display badges,
キャリーケースのハンドルに通せるように通し穴もあるので
and it has a sleeve to slip over suitcase handles,
旅行の時も片手で持ち運べると。すごいです、これ。
so you can carry it with one hand when traveling. This is amazing.
で、モチーフキーホルダーはキービジュアルの僕の首元にあるドッグタグというものをイメージしました
The motif keychain is modeled after the dog tag around my neck in the key visual.
かっこいいデザインなので、バッグやポーチにつけてみてください。
It's a cool design, so please attach it to your bags or pouches.
アクリルスタンドも、これもね、さっき見たら凄かった！
And the acrylic stand, I looked at it earlier and it's awesome!
背景の展開トラスと、かなたがそうがね、別パーツになってるんで
The background truss and Kanata are separate parts,
立体的に飾れてます。すごい立体感あった。もう4Dでしたね。
so you can display it in 3D. It has so much depth, it's basically 4D!
そしてそして、最後に注意事項です！
And finally, here are some important notes!
グッズの販売期間はこのあと21時から
The sales period for the merchandise starts today at 9 PM...
6月23日18時までです。
...and runs until June 23rd at 6 PM.
おんで、みんな、ややこしいからね、あれなんだけど注意してほしいのが
Also, everyone, it's a bit confusing, but please pay attention to this:
先行発送グッズはライブの前に届く予定なんですけど
The early-shipping goods are scheduled to arrive before the live,
受注販売グッズはライブ後、これあとなんですよ、受注販売グッズね。間違えないように
but the made-to-order goods arrive after the live. Don't mix them up!
チェックしてください。ぜひよろしくお願いします。
Please check carefully. We'd really appreciate your support.
詳しい情報は公式サイト、公式X、販売サイト、そして公式特設サイトをご確認ください。
Check the official website, official X, sales site, and special website!
告知は以上になります！
And that is all for the announcements!
ということで、ソロライブはしくじらないように頑張りたいと思います。
So, I'll do my absolute best not to mess up my solo live!
おね、ちょっと前にさ、エイプリルフールに双子の妹登場させたりしたじゃん？
You know, a while back on April Fools, I had my twin sister show up, right?
なんかあいつすごい人気なんかになったりとかしてね。
She ended up becoming super popular for some reason.
そういうね、ちょっと入れられてないしくじりとかも色々あるんですけど、
There are actually various ❝mess-ups❞ I couldn't include here, but...
これからのホロライブ人生、しくじることは確実にあると思いますが、
...while there will definitely be more mistakes in my future Hololive journey,
そんな天音かなたを、そして初めてのソロライブをよろしくお願いします！
I hope you'll support Amane Kanata and her very first solo live!
一緒にカートに入れたらアウト？わかんない、あとでちょっと調べとくわ。
Will placing them in the same cart mess it up? I'll look it up later.
みんなまた言うわ。ありがとね。ややこしいぞ、わかる。
I'll let you guys know later. Thank you! It is confusing, I get it.
ということでね。それじゃみんなまた、おつかなた！ありがとう！
Alright then. Well, see you all later! Otsu-Kanata! Thank you!
MVに飛んでくれ！
Go check out the MV!
やあ、バイバーイ！
Yeah! Bye-bye!
重大告知 しくじりかなたそ〜 僕みたいになるな！！
[Major Announcement: Shiku-jiri Kanata-so~ Don't end up like me!!]